## Telmo Menezes

83 rue Chardon-Lagache 75016 Paris, France

email: telmo@telmomenezes.com URL: http://telmomenezes.com

Born: May 27, 1976—Coimbra, Portugal

Nationality: Portuguese

## Current Appointment

Postdoc Researcher at the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS) / Centre d'Analyse et de Mathématique Sociales CAMS/EHESS

Collaborating with the ALGOPOL project – an interdisciplinary project that aims at presenting new ideas for interpreting, understanding and acting on information classification on the web.

### Education

2009 PhD in Computer Science, University of Coimbra (Highest Honors)

Thesis title: Evolutionary Computational Intelligence for Multi-Agent Simulations Jury members:

- · Ernesto Costa, PhD (Thesis advisor; Full Professor University of Coimbra)
- · Julian Miller, PhD (Lecturer University of York)
- · Luís Correia, PhD (Associate Professor University of Lisbon)
- · Rui Mendes, PhD (Assistant Professor University of Minho)
- · Francisco Pereira, PhD (Assistant Professor Instituto Superior de Engenharia de Coimbra)
- · Fernando Penousal Machado, PhD (Assistant Professor University of Coimbra)

The thesis abstract and the full version pdf file can be found at http://telmomenezes.com/phd.

BSc in Computer Science, University of Coimbra

During my internship at Critical Software, I developed a software module for NASA / Jet Propulsion Laboratory. This module was part of Xception, a fault injection tool used by NASA to test space probe computer systems – <a href="http://www.xception.org/products/case-study">http://www.xception.org/products/case-study</a>.

# Areas of Specialization / Research Interests

Complex Systems, Artificial Intelligence, Genetic Programming, Knowledge Graphs, Natural Language Processing.

### Publications in Peer-Reviewed Conferences and Journals

- Menezes, T. and Roth, C., Automatic Discovery of Agent Based Models: an Application to Social Anthropology, Advances in Complex Systems [accepted for publication]
  - Menezes, T. and Roth, C., Artificial Social Scientist: an Application to Marriage Networks, in Proc. of the Interdisciplinary Workshop on Information and Decision in Social Networks (WIDS 2012), MIT, Cambrige, MA, USA, November 2012
  - Menezes, T., Roth, C. and Hamberger, K., Finding Generators for Alliance Networks, in Proc. of ESSA 2012 8th Conference of the European Social Simulation Association, University of Salzburg, Austria, September 2012
- Menezes, T., Roth, C. and Cointet, J-P., Finding the Semantic-Level Precursors on a Blog Network, International Journal of Social Computing and Cyber-Physical Systems
  - Menezes, T., A process for mapping large directed networks to 2D images and its applications, Poster presentation at the European Conference on Complex Systems 2011, University of Vienna, Austria, 2011
  - Menezes, T., Evolutionary Modeling of a Blog Network, in Proc. of the IEEE 2011 Congress on Evolutionary Computation, New Orleans, USA, June 2011
- Menezes, T. and Roth, C. and Cointet, J-P., Precursors and Laggards: An Analysis of Semantic Temporal Relationships on a Blog Network, in Proc. of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Social Computing, SocialCom10, Minneapolis, USA, August 2010
- Menezes, T. and Costa, E., Coevolution of Competing Agent Species in a Gamelike Environment, in Proc. of the 1st European Workshop on Bio-inspired Algorithms in Games, EvoGAMES 2009, Tübigen, Germany, April 2009
- Menezes, T. and Costa, E., **Artificial Brains as Networks of Computational Building Blocks**, in Proc. of the 5th European Conference on Complex Systems, Jerusalem, Israel, September 2008
  - Menezes, T. and Costa, E., Modelling Evolvable Brains An Heterogeneous Network Approach, International Journal of Information Technology and Intelligent Computing, 2: 2, January 2008
- Menezes, T. and Costa, E., **Designing for Surprise**, in Proc. of the 9th European Conference on Artificial Life, ECAL 2007, Lisbon, September 2007
  - Menezes, T. and Costa, E., **The Gridbrain: an Heterogeneous Network for Open Evolution in 3D Environments**, in Proc. of the The First IEEE Symposium on Artificial Life, The First IEEE Symposium on Artificial Life, Honolulu, USA, April 2007
- Menezes, T. and Costa, E., A First Order Language to Coevolve Agents in Complex Social Simulations, in Proc. of the European Conference on Complex Systems 2006, Oxford, United Kingdom, September 2006

Baptista, T. and Menezes, T. and Costa, E., **BitBang: A Model and Framework** for Complexity Research, in Proc. of the European Conference on Complex Systems 2006, Oxford, United Kingdom, September 2006

Menezes, T. and Baptista, T. and Costa, E., **Towards the Generation of Complex Game Worlds**, in Proc. of the IEEE Symposium on Computational Intelligence and Games (CIG'06), Reno/Lake Tahoe, USA, May 2006

Menezes, T. and Costa, D. and Tavares, M., On the Extension of Xception to Support Software Fault Models, in Proc. of the International Symposium on Software Reliability Engineering (ISSRE2000), San Jose, USA, October, 2000.

Menezes, T. and Carreira, J., Experiment Management for the Xception Fault Injection Technology, in Proc. of the International Symposium on Software Reliability Engineering (ISSRE'99), Boca Raton, USA, November 1999.

Pedroso, H. and Silva, L. M. and Batista, V. and Martins, P. and Soares, G. and Menezes, T., **Parallel Computing over the Internet with Java**, in Proc. of the 3rd International Meeting on Vector and Parallel Processing (VECPAR'98), Oporto, Portugal, June 1998

### Invited Presentations

Menezes, T. **Agent Based Modelling of Genealogical Networks**, Colloque Final du Projet SimPa - Simulations de la Parenté, Paris, France, Oct 18-20, 2012

Menezes, T. Machine Learning Applied to Alliance Networks, Colloque Final du Projet SimPa - Simulations de la Parenté, Paris, France, Oct 18-20, 2012

Menezes, T. Evolving social graph models, ASSYST workshop "Hypernetworks, network dynamics, influence on networks: current tendency in social research", Warsaw, Poland, Dec 14-15, 2011

Menezes, T. Evolutionary modeling of complex networks, Complex Networks Seminars at LIP6, Paris 6 University, France, Nov 17, 2011

# Previous Research Appointments

2010-2012 Postdoc Researcher at the French National Center for Scientific Research (CNRS), more specifically:

Centre d'Analyse et de Mathématique Sociales CAMS/EHESS

Collaborated with the QLectives EU research project (http://qlectives.eu). QLectives aims at developing self-organising socially intelligent information systems, drawing inspiration from recent trends in information systems: social networks, peer production (e.g. wikis) and peer-to-peer systems. I worked on a novel method to perform evolutionary search for generative models that explain the dynamics of complex social networks.

Collaborated with the SIMPA project - Mathematical simulation and Kinship network analysis. The aim of SimPa is to arrive at an integrated model of the emergence of matrimonial circuits in kinship networks, and to develop simulation techniques for a realistic modelling of these networks that can be used by the researchers (anthropologists, demographers, historians and sociologists) who study them.

Complex Systems Institute - Paris Île de France (ISCPIF) / Center of Research in Applied Epistemology (CREA) - École Polytechnique

Collaborated with the Webfluence research project (http://webfluence.csregistry.org). Webfluenced studied the French blogosphere from a Complex Systems perspective, including morphogenesis phenomena, information broadcast processes and socio-semantic topological analysis. Under this collaboration I developed a set of algorithms that combine natural language processing with statistical analysis to automatically identify self-contained discussion topics within a corpus of data crawled from a blog network. I also developed a set of metrics to measure the tendency of bloggers to be precursors and laggards in terms of participation in discussion topics.

2004-2009

Researcher at the Evolutionary and Complex Systems Group of the University of Coimbra, Portugal

- · Evolutionary Computational Intelligence for Multi-Agent Simulations (PhD work)
- · MATER Territorial Self-Organization Models (Collaborator)

1998

Research Intern at the University of Coimbra, Portugal

· Parallel Scientific Computation with Java

## Teaching

2007-2009

BSc/MSc projects supervisor at the University of Coimbra

2000-2001

Teaching assistant at the University of Coimbra

## Industry Experience

2009

R&D Engineer, Taptu (Cambridge, UK based search engine for the mobile web)

2001-2003

Software Engineer (Artificial Intelligence), Ciberbit

1999-2001

Software Engineer, Critical Software (working on a project for NASA/JPL)

### Research Collaborations

2011

Consultant for the "IPinions Rank" project at Médialab, SciencesPo, Paris, France

#### Awards

2011

Winner of the data challenge competition of the *Mining the Digital Traces of Science - MDTS11* workshop, Paris, France

2010

### Service

- 2012- Reviewer for the journal Advances in Complex Systems
- Member of the program committee of IEEE 2012 Congress on Evolutionary Computation, 10/15 Jun, Brisbane, Australia
- Member of the program committee of DevLeaNN Workshop on Development and Learning in Artificial Neural Networks, 27/28 Oct, Paris, France

Member of the program committee of ALEA@EPIA2011, the 5th Workshop on Artificial Life and Evolutionary Algorithms, Portugal

Chair of the Clustering and Data Mining panel at the  $\it IEEE~2011~Congress~on~Evolution ary~Computation$ 

- Reviewer for MAEB 2010 VII Spanish Congress on Meta-heuristics and Evolutionary and Bio-inspired Algorithms
- Member of the technical program committee and reviewer for Complex'09 The First International Conference of Complex Sciences: Theory and Applications

## Open Source Scientific Tools

**Synthetic** (https://github.com/telmomenezes/synthetic): Genesis and dynamics of Complex Networks.

LabLOVE (http://telmomenezes.com/lablove): Artifical Life research tool.

### Technical Skills

- · Generic Programming Languages: C, C++, Java, Scala, Python, Objective-C, JavaScript, CoffeScript, PHP, ...
- · Scientific Programming Languages / Libraries: R, Matlab, NumPy/SciPy
- · Others: HTML/CSS, SQL and Relational Databases, NoSQL Databases (Riak, MongoDB), Mobile Application Development, Web Development, Distributed Systems